In my video on the problem with index
funds, I compared DFUS, a lowcost total
US market ETF that doesn't follow an
index, to VTI, a total US market index
ETF. To illustrate how not following an
index can be beneficial. Despite these
two ETFs being total market funds that
are similar along most dimensions, DFUS
has outperformed VTI since it listed as
an ETF in June 2021. Many people were
upset by the suggestion that index funds
are not perfect investments and wanted
to poke holes in my comparison. I think
this is worth digging into further. In
this video, I'm going to take a more
detailed look at these two funds and
explain why index funds, while an
incredible innovation, still have room
to improve. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital, and
I'm going to compare in more detail than
you probably want DFUS and VTI.
[Music]
Let me be clear about something upfront.
Lowcost total market index funds are
great tools for building portfolios. If
you're a happy index fund investor,
don't let this video push you off
course. I am a big fan of index funds,
but I'm also aware that they're not
perfect and this channel doesn't exist
to coddle the beliefs of index fund
investors. That said, in the grand
scheme of things, choosing between two
lowcost, low turnover, and broadly
diversified funds like DFUS and VTI is
probably not a decision that will change
your ability to meet your long-term
financial goals. It is, however, a
reminder that it's important not to be
dogmatic about anything in investing. I
get it. Index investing stems from a
scientific approach to thinking about
managing portfolios. It's rooted in
theories like Marowitz portfolio theory,
the capital asset pricing model, and the
efficient market hypothesis, and
supported by mountains of empirical
evidence demonstrating the inability of
active managers to beat index funds most
of the time. The weight of this theory
and evidence should make it very
difficult for people to update their
prior belief that index funds are
optimal investments. But even in the
face of a strong prior belief, applying
the same type of scientific thinking and
more up-to-date theory can lead to
modest improvements. DFUS is the
dimensional US equity market ETF, a US
total market fund that aims to deliver
market returns without following an
index. And while making a few
evidence-based tweaks to how the fund is
managed and implemented, VTI is the
Vanguard total stock market ETF, a US
total market fund that tracks the crisp
US total market index. Its sole
objective is tracking the performance of
that index net of costs. Both funds
offer broad exposure to the US market,
but by not following an index and doing
a few other things that I'll detail in a
minute, DFUS has been able to outperform
VTI since it launched as an ETF in June
2021 through July 15th, 2025, while
maintaining similar exposure to the
total US stock market. DFUS is not an
index fund, but it looks more like an
index fund than a traditional actively
managed fund. It differs from VTI in a
few nuanced, well-th thoughtout, and
important ways. First, index funds like
VTI follow rigid rebalancing rules to
match index returns, leading to some
potential costs that won't show up in
fees. A stock market index is a
representation of a stock market, but it
is not the stock market. Every day,
there are changes in market composition
due to things like initial public
offerings, new share issuance, and stock
buybacks. Most indexes rebalance to
reflect these changes quarterly. In
between rebalancings, the index and the
actual stock market will differ
slightly. The timing and nature of index
rebalancing ends up being really
important. The 2025 paper index
rebalancing and stock market
composition, do indexes time the market,
explains that indices and by extension
index funds are subject to adverse
selection due to when firms issue or buy
back stock? Firms, companies that list
on the stock market will issue stock
when they think their share price is
high and they'll buy back stock when
they think their share price is low.
It's a similar situation for IPOs. Firms
will go public when they believe their
share price is high. This makes sense
for firms and contains information for
investors in fulfilling their role of
representing the market. Total market
indexes quickly incorporate these
changes through their rebalancing
traits, buying stock when firms issue or
go public and selling when they buy
back. Index funds follow suit to fulfill
their role of closely tracking the
index. This puts index fund rebalancing
at odds with firms own beliefs about
their share prices and empirically it
results in an implicit cost for index
funds. The authors of this paper find
that the long short portfolios that
mirror index fund rebalancing trades
have a negative 3.5% annual return and
load negatively on the value
profitability and investment factors.
They estimate that this imposes a 60
basis point annual index level
performance drag on the total market
index. This can be thought of as the
cost for achieving the primary objective
of the index, which is to approximate
the returns of the market it represents.
It's not a cost that's easy to see
because it's equally reflected in the
returns of the index and the index fund.
One of the ways this paper measures the
cost of index rebalancing is by
constructing index portfolios that
rebalance less frequently and implement
a lag in incorporating changes in market
composition. These lazy indexes, as
they're called in the paper, boost
returns by 40 to 60 basis points per
year. A benefit mostly stemming from
waiting to incorporate changes in market
composition. Another interesting point
that the authors make is that both
normal quarterly rebalanced indexes and
the lazy rebalanced indexes that are
introduced in the paper have tracking
error relative to the actual stock
market. But lazy rebalancing improves
the return per unit of tracking error.
This is a fascinating point. An index is
not the market. Its returns are not
identical to the returns of the market.
In other words, it has tracking error to
the market. This is because the index
reflects changes to market composition
quarterly while actual market changes
are daily. A lazy index is even further
away from being the market because it
further delays incorporating changes to
market composition. But the increase in
tracking error is relatively less
significant than the increase in
expected returns. This is because the
lazy index is mechanically avoiding
buying stocks with low expected returns
and selling stocks with high expected
returns in response to changes in market
composition. Well, it's not quite a lazy
index as defined in this paper. By not
tracking an index at all, DFUS is able
to avoid this issue almost entirely.
DFUS delays buying IPOs and it follows
trading rules designed to increase
expected returns rather than trading to
match changes in market composition. It
also excludes certain types of stocks
entirely. These exclusions are important
to understand in making the DFUS to VTI
comparison. DFUS excludes small cap
growth stocks with weak profitability,
small cap growth stocks with aggressive
investment, and small cap stocks with
high securities lending fees. These
specific types of small cap stocks are
well known for having poor returns.
They're sometimes referred to as junk or
small crap growth stocks. The exclusions
in DFUS are not intended specifically to
avoid the effects of adverse selection
on changes in market composition, but
they do have an interesting interaction
with that research. In index rebalancing
and stock market composition, the
authors find that one of the reasons
that index fund rebalancing portfolios
perform poorly is because of their
factor exposures. These same factor
exposures are minimized by DFUS's
exclusions. DFUS also excludes REITs.
This exclusion is not based on any
particular evidence. It's simply a
product design choice by dimensional. If
people want to add REITs, they can do so
easily with a REIT ETF. REITs were one
of the common arguments I saw against my
comparison of DFUS and VTI in my
previous video. Some comments suggested
that the REIT exclusion explains all of
the performance difference over my
sample period. To address this, I built
a model portfolio that consists of DFUS
combined with VNQ, the Vanguard Real
Estate ETF, where the weight of VNQ in
my model is matched to the historical
weight of REITs in VTI. As you can see,
adding the real estate allocation to
DFUS does drag down returns over this
period, but there's still a huge portion
of excess return that can be attributed
to exclusions and avoiding adverse
selection. Interestingly, the 60 basis
point excess return after adjusting for
read exposure is identical to the
findings in index rebalancing and stock
market composition. It's also important
to understand how much of the market
DFUS excludes. This speaks to another
comment that I saw some people making
that DFUS is missing out on a large
portion of the US market, making it an
unwise investment choice. This argument
seems like it could make sense if you
look only at the number of securities in
the two ETFs. When I collected the data
for this video, VTI held 3564
stocks while DFUS held 2430. With more
than a thousand fewer holdings, it looks
like DFUS is covering much less of the
US stock market. But before drawing
conclusions here, it's important to
understand the market weight of the
stocks being excluded from DFUS. VTI
covers approximately 100% of the US
stock market reflective of its
underlying total market index. DFUS is
not tracking an index at all. It's
benchmarked against another US market
index, the Russell 3000. But the
universe of stocks that DFUS selects
from are not tied to that index. DFUS
holds 179 stocks that are not included
in the Russell 3000 and excludes 661
stocks that are included in the Russell
3000. The Russell 3000 covers roughly
98% of the US stock market and DFUS is
excluding 3.6% of the market cap weight
covered by the Russell 3000. As you can
see, while there are fewer stocks by
number, they make up a tiny portion of
the market. Another thing is that a big
portion of that 3.6% exclusion relative
to the Russell 3000, roughly 2.6 six
percentage points of it is rates which
we talked about earlier. The remaining
1% are the previously mentioned small
cap exclusions. Over this period, the
excluded small cap stocks have returned
about -10% annualized at a 1% weight in
the portfolio. This represents a
negative0.1%
contribution from the excluded stocks
leaving a large portion of the excess
returns to be explained by things like
trading flexibility and avoiding adverse
selection on index rebalancing. The
other argument I want to address is that
while I focused on the returns of DFUS
since it listed as an ETF in June 2021,
it did trade as a mutual fund prior to
that. And over the full period since
inception, it has underperformed VTI
from inception on September 25th, 2001
through June 11th, 2021, prior to DFUS
listing as an ETF. VTI outperformed the
predecessor to DFUS, which at the time
traded as a mutual fund with the ticker
DTMEX by an annualized 0.47%.
Whether this preetf listing performance
means that the post ETF listing
performance has just been luck is a
valid question that requires
understanding where the difference came
from. DTMEX was similar to DFUS in many
ways, but there were some differences
that I think are material enough to make
the preetf conversion data difficult to
extrapolate from. DTMEX was still a
total market fund, but its objective was
to maximize tax efficiency. DFUS does
share this objective, but DTMEX
accomplished the objective in different
ways. For some of its history, it held
lower dividend yield stocks. It was also
careful to avoid unqualified dividends
and short-term capital gains by holding
stocks for longer than it would have
otherwise. Fast forward to today, DFUS
no longer aims to hold low dividend
yield stocks. And under the ETF
structure in the US, there are now more
efficient ways for the fund to deal with
capital gains. The other issue with the
pre-ETF comparison to VTI is that DTMEX
had a much higher expense ratio than VTI
for most of their shared lives. Back in
2001, DTMEX had an expense ratio of
0.25% while VTI was at 0.15%.
But by 2018, VTI was down to 0.03% while
DTMEX was at 0.22%
for a 0.19%
difference. When DTMEX began trading as
an ETF, DFUS, its expense ratio dropped
to 0.09%, only 0.06% higher than VTI.
Another issue with the historical data
is the exclusions. The current
exclusions being applied in DFUS stem
from research that had not been done yet
when DTMEX was launched. The exclusions
were added to DTMEX over time, but they
were not there for the full sample.
Overall, I don't think the pre and post
ETF conversion data are comparable. DFUS
is materially different from DTMEX on
multiple measures. All things
considered, while I do acknowledge that
data going back to June 2021 are not
sufficient to draw long-term conclusions
from, I don't think that the prior
history of this fund predating its ETF
conversion is representative of its
expected performance. This fund's
approach and performance contain
important information for investors to
consider. Total market index funds are
great investments because they are
lowcost, low turnover, broadly
diversified, and tax efficient. But
these favorable characteristics are not
exclusive to index funds. Indexes are
designed to be representations of the
stock market. Index funds blindly follow
them with the objective of matching
their performance. Recent research has
shown that due to the timing of changes
in market composition stemming from
things like share buybacks, share
issuance, and IPOs, total market indexes
are effectively bad market timers. An
index that delays incorporating changes
in market composition and considers the
expected returns of the stocks that it
owns can increase expected returns. This
is very different from traditional
active management which aims to beat the
market by picking relatively
concentrated portfolios of stocks or
timing exposure to the market.
Traditional active management has higher
fees and costs to overcome and by
holding concentrated portfolios often
fewer than 100 stocks risks missing out
on the subset of stocks that drive most
of the market's performance. This leads
to underperformance for most active
funds even before fees and costs are
considered. DFUS is still a total market
fund. It is lowcost, low turnover,
broadly diversified and tax efficient.
It does exclude some stocks
intentionally based on their expected
return profile, but it still holds
thousands of stocks. Between its
exclusions and its ability to avoid the
market timing costs that affect total
market index funds, DFUS represents
structural improvements to the already
incredible lowcost total market index
fund. The cost of being different from
the index, even if it does lead to
expected outperformance, is tracking
error. Performance that is different
from the index can be challenging for
investors. For example, I could make
this video and DFUS could go on to
underperform VTI for some period of
time. Even people who found the
arguments in the video compelling might
have trouble sticking with the strategy
through periods of underperformance
relative to well-known indexes. This is
likely a reason that many people will
not, and I might even say should not
pursue a non-indexed total market
strategy like DFUS. If you can get over
the possibility of tracking error and
are willing to update your beliefs about
the best way to invest, I do think it's
possible to make slight improvements to
the already great concept of lowcost
total market index funds. And I think
that is exactly what DFUS is doing.
Thanks for watching. I'm Ben Felix, CIO
at PWL Capital. Tell me how dogmatic
your beliefs about index funds are in
the comments.